בוקר טוב. Boker tov.
47th day in the עומר. Omer. Oh my gosh, it's almost שבועות.
Shavuos. All right. So today's דף daf is דף ט, daf tes,
and we pick up in the bottom half of ח׳ עמוד ב׳,
ches amud beis, and we're in the middle of discussing the different
types of lands that different people who are owed money are entitled
to. The person who is damaged gets the best quality, the עידית,
idis, the בעל חוב, bal chov, the creditor gets the בינונית, beinonis,
middle quality, for כתובה, kesuvah, it's the זיבורית, ziboris, it's the worst
quality, and different interesting types of scenarios about what happens if they're
sold off, and then how that might affect who gets what. Okay.
So now
we pick up in the middle of ח׳ עמוד ב׳, ches amud
beis, and אמר רבא, Amar Rava, the line starts with רבא, Rava,
it's across from the תוספות דינא, Tosfos Dina, two lines above that,
it's about if I'd have to guess 20 lines from the bottom
of the page. Okay, אמר רבא, Amar Rava, ראובן שמכר כל שדותיו
לשמעון, Reuven shemachar kol sadosav leShimon, so Reuven sold off his fields
to Shimon, והלך שמעון ומכר שדה אחת ללוי. vehalach Shimon umachar sade
achas leLevi. Now Shimon came and sold one field to Levi. All
right. ובא בעל חוב דראובן. Uva bal chov deReuven. So we're no
longer here dealing with A, B, and C questions, quality of lands.
We're dealing with a simple question of
who can you collect the land from? Because now Levi comes, ובא
בעל
חוב דראובן, uva bal chov deReuven, excuse me, not Levi, Reuven's creditor
comes. So Reuven's creditor comes, and who is he going to get
the land from? Now presumably you'd think he'd get it from Reuven.
But as we're going to see in a minute, he can't get
it from Reuven for whatever reason. Reuven doesn't have any בינונית. beinonis.
Reuven doesn't have that quality, that grade of land that he's entitled
to. So he has to get it from Shimon or from Levi.
Okay. Can Levi say, "No, buddy, you've got to get it from
Shimon. I'm the last guy in the line."? Or can the בעל
חוב bal chov say, "What do I care?
I'm exercising
my liens. Reuven doesn't have it, so I'm just going to get
the land from wherever it's most convenient, whether you're the first purchaser
or the second purchaser."? So let's see what it
says. Okay. ובא בעל חוב דראובן רצה מזה גובה רצה מזה גובה.
Uva bal chov deReuven, ratza mizeh goveh, ratza mizeh goveh. If he
wants, he can collect from either one, from either Shimon or Levi.
From his perspective, the land is, he has a right to exercise
his liens, he has a lien on those lands. What does he
care whether he's getting it, and once he's not getting it from
Reuven, you get the idea that you have to go to Reuven
first, once you're not getting it from Reuven, what do you care
whether it's Shimon or Levi? So that's the whole statement of רבא.
Rava. Now it's going to be interesting, and I didn't point this
out yesterday, but you also saw this yesterday. I don't know if
you noticed that some of the passage yesterday seemed to be a
little bit wordy, or at least much more fully articulated than other
passages of גמרא. Gemara. It was a lot of straight Aramaic language.
So there's an interesting question here about how much some of the
stuff we're reading is
a later gloss. So you have this statement of רבא, Rava, now
you're going to get a whole big Aramaic passage here, not Hebrew.
The statement we just said was basically Hebrew. That's going to very
much qualify the parameters in which this is true, that it's רצה
מזה גובה רצה מזה גובה. ratza mizeh goveh, ratza mizeh goveh. So
let's take a look. ולא אמרינן, Velo amrin, we only said this,
אלא דזבן בינונית. ela dezaven beinonis. If this field that Shimon got
is a בינונית beinonis field, and remember, the בעל חוב bal chov
is entitled to
בינונית. beinonis. That Levi, did I say Shimon? The field that Levi
bought is a בינונית. beinonis. Okay. Then the בעל חוב bal chov
is entitled to בינונית. beinonis. So the בעל חוב bal chov can
go either to Shimon or to Levi, if Levi actually has a
בינונית beinonis field. Okay. אבל זבן עידית וזיבורית, Aval zaven idis veziboris,
but if Levi went ahead and purchased A-quality and C-quality lands,
so then he can say. Now why can't the בעל חוב bal
chov say, "Look, buddy, I have a right to B-quality. You're more
convenient, I'll just take the זיבורית ziboris from you."? I understand that
I can't go up and demand the עידית, idis, but Shimon's lands
are in an inconvenient place, or he's hard to bring to the
בית דין beis din or whatever, so I'm just going to go
to you and take the זיבורית. ziboris. I'll go down a level.
So no, he can't do that. אבל זבן עידית וזיבורית לא דאמר
ליה להכי דייקי וזבני עידית וזיבורית. Aval zaven idis veziboris lo, de'amar
lei, lehachi deiki vezavni idis veziboris. חזי לך. chazi lach. That's why
I made a point of only buying A and C, because I
wanted to make sure that I was not taking the type of
a land that you as a בעל חוב baal chov had rights
to, okay? So it's similar to the idea that you can't go
to Shimon before you went to the guy who owes you money
himself. And here he's basically saying you can't move on from Shimon.
Maybe if it's all equivalent you can, but if I specifically left
you the land that you have your primary liens on, you can't
come to me. You can't say I'm going to go down to
grade C. Okay, thank you. ואפילו זבין בינונית נמי לא אמרן אלא
דלא שייר בינונית דכוותה. Ve-afilu zavin benonis nami lo amran ela de-lo
shayer benonis dikvasah. But here's the big חידוש. chiddush. Even if he
bought B, he says okay, you bought B, so I now have
a right to B quality land. Reuven doesn't have anything, I'm going
to go to you. Why do I need to go to Shimon?
No, even that דלא מצי... de-lo matzi... it would only be true
if Shimon was not left with any B quality land. If Shimon
has only like A and C quality land, then you can say
my primary lien is on B, you're the guy that has B,
I'm coming to you. Okay, אלא דלא שייר
בינונית דכוותה דלא מצי אמר ליה, ela de-lo shayer benonis dikvasah de-lo
matzi amar leh, because otherwise he would have been able to say
הנחתי לך מקום לגבות משמעון. hinachti lecha makom ligvos mi-Shimon. No, you
can't come to me. I left some B quality in the hands
of Shimon and you have to go to Shimon before you go
to me. So notice we have just completely undermined what Rava said.
Okay, at least the פשט pshat of what Rava said. Rava says
רצה מזה גובה רצה מזה גובה, ratza mi-zeh goveh ratza mi-zeh goveh,
which at least minimally would give us the impression that if they
both had B quality land, the בעל חוב baal chov is entitled
to choose who he wants to go to. And what we have
said is that's not true. That if they both have B quality
land, Levi can say you gotta go to Shimon before going to
me. And the only time Rava said רצה מזה גובה רצה מזה
גובה ratza mi-zeh goveh ratza mi-zeh goveh was if the B quality
was Levi. So then the בעל חוב baal chov could say I
have a right to go to you because my primary lien is
on B quality land, or if I want to I can also
go to Shimon because I'm also entitled to C quality land. Okay,
so as opposed to Rava which really made it sound like it's
your choice, certainly all things being equal, we're saying that's not true.
If they both have B quality, you gotta go to Shimon, you
don't go to Levi. אבל שייר בינונית דכוותה גבי שמעון, Aval shayer
benonis dikvasah gabei Shimon, but if he left also B quality by
Shimon, לא גבי מיניה, lo gabei minei, then the בעל חוב baal
chov cannot go to Levi, דמצי אמר ליה de-matzi amar leh Levi
can say to the בעל חוב, baal chov, הנחתי לך מקום לגבות
הימנו. hinachti lecha makom ligvos heimenu. You know what? I left over
B quality in the hand of Shimon, he comes before me. All
right, so basically now what we've said is is that the בעל
חוב baal chov has to first go to Reuven. If Reuven doesn't
have, he has to go to the first level purchasers, not the
first person that bought from Reuven. If a lot of people bought
directly from Reuven, he has to go to the first level purchasers.
And only if none of the first level purchasers have grade B,
can he move on to the second level purchasers. Okay, that's how
we've interpreted what Rava said. Moving on. אמר אביי: Amar Abaye: ראובן
שמכר שדה לשמעון. Reuven she-machar sadeh le-Shimon. Now we're going to have
a bit of a different type of an issue. Reuven sold the
field to Shimon באחריות. be-achrayus. And now we're introducing something we have
not introduced now, what I was calling before insurance, loosely called insurance.
What it basically means is, okay, Michael comes here and buys a
land from me, but he says, Dov, I know you got a
lot of outstanding debts. So what's going to happen if somebody's going
to come and take that land from the money you owe them?
I insist that when I buy this land from you, that I
have a lien against your remainder property. That's the אחריות, achrayus, a
lien against your remainder property to be reimbursed if that land is
ever taken from me in payment for your debts. Okay, that's called
באחריות. be-achrayus. So like he sort of gets an insurance against that
land being taken to pay off my debts, and that gives him
liens on the remainder of my property. Right, so that's what I
did. So I went ahead,
ראובן Reuven sold field to שמעון Shimon here באחריות, be-achrayus, and שמעון
Shimon now has a lien against ראובן's Reuven fields if that field
is ever seized in payment of debt. ואתא בעל חוב דראובן, Ve-asa
baal chov de-Reuven, now Reuven's creditor lo and behold comes along, וטרף
משמעון, ve-taraf mi-Shimon, and takes that field from Shimon. So Shimon's now
going to turn around and get his money back from Reuven. So
דינא הוא דאזיל ראובן
ומשתעי דינא בהדיה, Dina hu de-azil Reuven u-mishta'ei dina bahadei, that Reuven
can come, so now Jacob's there, you know, who was my בעל
חוב, baal chov, took Michael's field to pay off the money I
owed him. I can come to court
and protest or, you know, be a... the question that we're dealing
with is something that's called in law standing, right? Who has standing
to bring a case? Who is entitled to actually be there as
a litigant? Right? If I can't just come say like I'm upset
about the law about abortion, I'm going to bring a case in
front of the Supreme Court. Like I have to be a בעל
דבר, baal davar, right? It has to be my issue, right? It
has to affect me. So here Michael is before he comes to
me to get paid back, he's going to fight against Jacob and
try to defend the fact that maybe money isn't owed and Jacob
isn't entitled to... take the field and so on. I can come
to court and I can be on Michael's team and I can
also, even though you're not out taking the money from me, you're
directly taking it from him, I can come ahead and say here's
why you're not entitled to take that money, here's why I don't
really owe you the money and so on. Okay, now that should
be like relatively obvious for two reasons. Number one is because Michael's
going to come back to me, so I am going to be
affected by this. And number two actually is he's getting the money
from Michael because I owe him the money, you know, but that
might but seems from the גמרא Gemara that wasn't enough. Okay, so
דינא, dina, the law is דאזיל ראובן ומשתעי דינא בהדיה, de-azil Reuven
u-mishtaei dina bahadei, that ראובן Reuven can come and, you know, and
be a litigant with against the בעל חוב baal chov to protect,
you know, שמעון Shimon's field from being seized. ולא מצי אמר ליה
ve-lo matzi amar lei and the בעל חוב baal chov can't say
to them לאו בעל דברים דידי את, lav baal devarim didi at,
"Hey though, this isn't any of your business. I'm collecting the field
from Michael, you stay out of it." No. דאמר ליה, de-amar lei,
I can say back, אי מפקת מיניה עלי הדר, ei mafkat minei
alai hadar, if you take that field away from Michael, he's going
to come back to me to ask to be reimbursed. So of
course it affects me, I better come here to defend him. ואיכא
דאמרי ve-ika de-amri and some say אפילו שלא באחריות נמי, afilu she-lo
be-achrayus nami,
even if I don't haven't promised to reimburse Michael, I don't haven't
committed to reimburse Michael. דאמר ליה de-amar lei because I can still
say to my creditor, לא ניחא לי דליהוי לשמעון תרעומת עלי. lo
nicha li de-leihavei le-Shimon taromas alai. Look, legally I won't owe him
any money, but he's going to have a complaint against me. It's
going to hurt my reputation. I am affected. He's going to be
blaming me for this. So just that I'm going to be blamed
makes me enough affected. Now one does wonder, is it also compounded
with the fact that the only reason the בעל חוב baal chov
is going to שמעון Shimon is because of the money that I
owe him? Right? I mean I don't know if you could imagine
another case where it was not coming through something that I, you
know, was my obligation. Somebody is just going to, I don't know,
you know, come to Michael here because of some other thing and
it was based on, I don't know, somehow I'm saying you know
what if he wins that case I'm going to look bad, not
because I was involved in that case, it's just people are going
to have complaints against me. Does that make me a בעל דין?
baal din? Like I would question that. Here there's two things going
on. Number one is is that the reason this בעל חוב baal
chov has a case against Michael is because of money I owe
him, and I'm not totally out of the picture
because actually Michael will blame me for this because it is coming
through me. Alright, so I don't think it's just the תרעומת. taromas.
I think it also has to do with the fact that the
case is because of the money that I borrowed. Yes, Jacob?
You just said that if this was a normal case without אחריות
achrayus that if I wanted to go collect from Michael, then Michael
couldn't go
back, if there's no אחריות achrayus he can't go back, correct. I
know, if there's no, essentially no insurance? No, the sale was a
sale, you bought the land knowing that there were liens against it.
That's the risk you took. You knew there were liens against it,
right? I mean I don't know, would people know what the law
is in general when you buy land with liens, right? When those
liens get exercised, you don't get your money back from the person
you bought it from, right? Those are and those are the risks
that you assume.
You usually satisfy the lien before you can register the transfer.
Alright, if I have a lien against my land, yeah, and you
want to buy it from me, I can't sell it to you
with the lien?
Yeah, you have to have the person who made the lien
agree
that the lien's been satisfied.
Now there the way I'm not
a
lawyer, but
there there are ways to work around that like let's say the
lien is the mortgage. Yes. Sometimes the mortgage can be transferred to
the new owner along with the lien. Right. But that requires the
agreement of the person who made who lent the money.
So it's basically the opposite.
It's basically it's all it's like it's automatically it usually is that
I have to get rid of the lien, but if we stipulate
then we can,
what mortgages are not transferred?
Right, so it's true. I mean this is a funny system, right?
It's a system that basically anybody who buys land that for from
a person who owes money, right, is taking a real like a
risk that that land he'll lose that land that he's now and
what happens? I mean there's גמרות gemaras that discuss that. I bought
a plot of land from you, I now built a high-rise condominium,
somebody's going to come now, you know, 10 years, 100 years later,
50 years later and take it from me because of money you
owe? So it's a, yeah, it's a good question. Go back to
that. Go back to that. Well that's true. So anyway, so, but
yes, but the but within this system, okay, I understand your moral
objection to the idea that, you know, what do you mean, he
didn't owe the money, but that's the risk you're assuming. You're assuming
that risk and you have to factor that in, oh, right you
have to factor that in to the purchase price. Now right, now
the whole reason that אחריות achrayus only exists by a שטר shtar
is because effectively there have to it has to be registered, you
know, there have to be public knowledge. The problem is, just because
there's a שטר, shtar, right, so my creditor's holding the שטר shtar
against you, you can't go to any central registry to do a
title search to make sure, so it's not really a perfect system.
And actually it's an interesting question which I never actually for whatever
reason never asked, which is if you're about to buy land from
me, can you actually like get assurances from me that there are
no liens against it? I assume you could do it בתנאי. bitnai.
You could always make a stipulation. I am buying this on the
assumption that there are no liens against this land. If it turns
out that there's no liens, then this sale is void.
And then you're entitled to it anyway?
Right, right, but if you didn't say it, we would say דברים
שבלב אינם דברים. devarim shebalev einam devarim. If you didn't articulate it,
we would say, "Hey buddy, your responsibility to check for the liens,"
right? But if you explicitly stipulate, yes, then you could void the
sale and get the money back. But this is, you didn't explicitly
stipulate it, it was your responsibility to find out and those were
the risks that you assumed. Dov, did you have a question before?
No? Okay.
Yeah? Check law, it's the responsibility of the lien holder to tell
the government to register the lien against the
land, which usually happens when the property is bought. A mortgage is
put on and it gets registered.
So let me just ask, I don't want to get too much
into this, but let me just ask one more question of clarification.
What is the point of a lien? If I owe money to
the bank, right, and the bank has a mortgage on my house
or whatever, right, what is the point of having that as a
mortgage and a lien rather than just like I owe them money,
they'll just and I can't pay, they'll just send the sheriff after
me and seize from whatever property of mine they can
find?
Might be easier to seize secured property
when
there's a lien.
I see. I see. It's less get, it just gets them like
at what like much further along in the process essentially.
And it prevents me from selling that asset to get out of
it.
I see. I see. Okay. All right. Moving on. All right.
Okay. Now, ואמר אביי, ve'amar Abaye, אביי Abaye also said, ראובן שמכר
שדה לשמעון שלא באחריות. Reuven shemachar sadeh leShimon shelo be'achrayus. ראובן Reuven
sold his field to שמעון Shimon without אחריות. achrayus. So שמעון Shimon
is not protected against what will happen if it gets seized. ויצאו
לה עסקין. veyatzu lah iskin.
Now, let's say, and this is going to be about, so I
went ahead and I sold my field here to Michael
and as we're going to see, soon after the sale or right
around the time of sale, my title to that field is being
challenged. Okay. Now, as we know, sometimes these things get held up
in the court for like years or decades, right? So he now
realizes that he bought a piece of land that there is going
to be, he's going to be in the courts for years and
years and years dealing with this issue. But it was after I
sold it to him. Can he come back to me and try
to say, "Oh, oh, wait, I want to back out on the
sale"? Okay. So עד שלא החזיק בה, ad shelo hechzik bah, before
he's done yet a חזקה chazakah on that land, יכול לחזור בה,
yachol lachzor bah, he can say, "Wait, I'm backing out." משהחזיק בה,
mishehechzik bah, once he's done a חזקה, chazakah, אין יכול לחזור בה,
ein yachol lachzor bah, he can't back out. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama,
why? דאמר ליה, de'amar lei, because I can say to him, חייא
דקטרי סברת וקבלת, chaysa dekitri savat vekabalt, which is basically the way
of saying like buyer beware. A bag filled with knots is what
you bought. You got yourself, it's got to be an idiomatic expression,
but basically it means
like sorry buddy, that was your risk, this is what you bought,
the sale was final, turns out that there is now this title
is being challenged or whatever,
that was what you brought upon, that's what you got, that's what
you bought, that's your responsibility. Okay. There is an English expression like
this, "a bag of goods," I think is what I'm thinking of.
You know, he sold me a bag of goods, right? Is it
a bill of goods? He sold me a bill of goods. Okay.
Anyway, so here you sold him a bag of goods. I sold
you a bag filled with knots, okay, instead of filled with gold
or whatever, but that's what you got. All right. Anyway, the sale's
final. Now, מאימתי הוי חזקה, me'eimatai havi chazakah, now when is the
חזקה chazakah that he can't back out? מכי דייש אמצרי, michidayesh amitzrei,
when he walks around the borders. Now I want to pause here
for a second. אבן העזר? Even HaEzer? thank you. So רש"י Rashi
says the חזקה chazakah we're talking about is the classic חזקה chazakah
of taking possession, and that this is a חזקה chazakah of like,
now normal חזקה chazakah though is when you actually do something to
fix the field. Here you're just walking around it. So תוספות Tosafos
asks two things. Number one is like, first of all, what's the
חידוש chiddush that the sale is final when the sale is final?
We always know that you have to do an act of taking
possession. And number two, this isn't the standard definition of חזקה. chazakah.
So תוספות Tosafos says we're actually not talking about standard חזקה. chazakah.
This is sort of like an idea, תוספות Tosafos doesn't use these
words but I will, sort of like an idea of a type
of a תוך כדי דיבור, toch kedei dibbur, a period of time
even after the sale is technically final that you can still back
out if some huge problem emerges within that time. Okay. So therefore,
and what is that time? Until you've had a chance to do
a little survey and a walking around of the field. So you
already did your חזקה chazakah or you already paid your money, I'll
get to the money in a minute, whatever it is.
אגבה תורא ופרק, agbah tora u'farak, that happened.
Okay. I sold the field to Michael, you did an אגבה תורא
ופרק, agbah tora u'farak, and then come within two hours, all of
a sudden you found out that there's a big challenge to the
title of this field. Ah, since you have not yet done The
ritual walking around, you're still in this period of time that you
can back out if you want. It's sort of like, now again,
like when you're in, when you buy a house.
You have to actually walking around?
You have to actually walk around. Until you have walked around...
and I could just withhold doing that for years?
Yeah, I don't know, obviously there's probably some limit to that, okay?
But when I, so I don't know the answer to that, but
there's a certain period of time that you have. Now it's sort
of like what, I know somebody, I have a relative who did
this, like he was saw this house, you won't believe the story.
He was passing by this house, he saw for sale sign, he
walked in, like he, you know, he thought this was like this
tremendous deal, okay, whatever they were selling for, I don't know, it
was somewhere in Brooklyn where I think a million dollars was a
tremendous deal. Anyway, whatever it was, okay, and he like he didn't
have time to get, it was before you take photos or whatever,
he couldn't get in touch with his wife. So right on the
spot he like signed the papers and he figured like anyway you
have a week or something between the time of signing the papers
and doing something, what is it, a title search or a building
inspects, some type of thing you have to do that if that
until that time you actually can back out even if you signed
the papers. So he figured I'll get her permission after I've done
this and then I can go back out. She wasn't happy, but
at the end of the day they got the house. So anyway,
I think she was happy in the end. But the point being
that you could actually, he was in a position where the sale
was final if he wanted it to be final, right? But because
certain things hadn't been done yet, he could back out even after
he had signed the papers. So that actually, do people know what
I'm talking about, what this...
You take a mortgage and you have to do the same thing,
you have to sign all these papers and stuff
and then you have whatever three days that you can back out
for no reason. Right, but that, but that's only a one-sided sort
of opportunity, right? You have the right to back out, they don't.
So this is the same idea. Even after the sale is final,
until this extra thing is done, okay, the survey is done or
whatever, you the buyer can back out if some big problem emerges.
That's the way תוספות Tosafot understands what this what this
is, okay? Now דאוקמה בשלא באחריות. D'ukma b'shelo b'achrayut. Now that the
fact that you have only until that time is when he bought
it without אחריות. achrayut. So he won't be able to get reimbursed.
אבל באחריות לא. Aval b'achrayut lo. But if you bought it with
אחריות, achrayut, presumably he can back out even later. Okay, why? Because
he can say look, if it winds up that this field wasn't
yours, you're going to take it from me, I'm going to ask
you for the money back. So since I'm anyway going to have
a right to ask you for the money back, I want to
back out right now.
Okay, now תוספות Tosafot says, and this is sort of like your
question Michael, what's the limit of this? One minute, you mean that
if I sell a field באחריות, b'achrayut, 20 years later there's some
problem you can say now I want to back out because there's
a problem and I bought it with אחריות achrayut so you might
as well just give me the money now? So תוספות Tosafot also
wants to limit this. He says that this might be limited to
cases before you've actually paid for the field. Once you've actually paid,
not. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara isn't clear about that, okay? But with,
if it's with אחריות achrayut since you're entitled to get the money
back if it is taken from you, you might be able to
have you have more time to actually back out of the deal.
Okay, and the גמרא Gemara says ואיכא דאמרי אפילו באחריות נמי. V'ika
d'amri afilu b'achrayut nami. No,
even if it was with אחריות, achrayut, you do not have more
time to back out of the deal than the surveying. דאמר להו
אותיב טרפך ואשלם לך. D'amar lehu otiv tarfakh v'ashalem lakh.
Because I can say to Michael now who wants to back out
now that there's been this challenge to the field, you know what
Michael, when you show me that בית דין Beit Din has awarded
the field to somebody else and has decided that it wasn't mine,
then I'll pay you back. I'll pay you back when the field
is taken from you. Until that time, it's your field and you
have to now deal with it in court. Okay, so the biggest
חידוש chiddush here is that even after the purchase of the real
estate, if some huge problem emerges, you can back out until, until
you've done some surveying of the land. Presumably there's a, there's a
calendar limit to that as well. Okay, that is the end of
a significant digression that we had around different types of paying up
of lands and בעל חוב ba'al chov and כתובת אשה ktuvat isha
and different grades of land, etc. Now we are going back about
two דפים dappim to the question of the seeming contradiction between on
the one hand מיטב שדהו meitav sadehu and on the other hand
כסף ישיב לבעליו אפילו סובין. kesef yashiv l'ba'alav afilu subin. Right, even
it could be like you know bran. So do you have to
give the best or can you give anything? And if you remember
the resolution we left with is the best if it's land, if
it's chattel it can be anything. So now we're going to get
a nuance on that position. Let's take a look. איתיבי רב נחמן
לרב הונא. Eitivei Rav Nachman l'Rav Huna. I'm sorry, I skipped a
line. רב הונא אמר או כסף או מיטב. Rav Huna amar o
kesef o meitav. רב הונא Rav Huna forgets the סובין subin story.
He says either land or cash. Okay,
so whatever happened to the idea that we said you could pay
even in, in junk? We'll see that in a minute. But he
says either you're paying land, okay, or if you're not paying land,
you gotta pay cash.
A man owes another guy.
Exactly, I guess so. Anyway, איתיבי רב נחמן לרב הונא. Eitivei Rav
Nachman l'Rav Huna. What do you mean? We said earlier, ישיב לרבות
שוה כסף אפילו סובין. Yashiv l'rabot shaveh kesef afilu subin. You should
return the money, but return means anything you want to give, even
bran, even like
the lousy property, whatever, like cheap stuff, as long as it is
as we said, chattel. But you're saying you can't pay back נזיקין
Nezikin with anything; you can only pay it back with land or
with cash. So he said, הכי במאי עסקינן דלית ליה ארעא. hachi
be-mai askinan de-leit lei ara. That's only if you don't have cash.
You first have—if you have land or cash, you gotta give land
or cash. If you have neither land or cash, then you give
whatever you have. So the גמרא Gemara says, אי דלית ליה, ee
de-leit lei, but wait, if you have nothing else, פשיטא, pishita, of
course, what else are you going to pay with? It's all you've
got; all you got is paper clips. No, מהו דתימא, mah u
deteyma, I might have thought that we can say to the ניזק,
Nizak, זיל טרח זבין ואייתי ליה
כסף. Zil tarach zavin ve-aiti lei kesef. No, you don't—you can't give
the guy paper clips; you sell the paper clips and pay him
in cash. You're obligated to pay him in cash; that's a reasonable
thing to say. קא משמע לן Kamashmalan that we don't; if you
have nothing else, you can give him whatever you've got. Okay, but
if you've got land, it's got to be the best land, and
if you've got cash, you gotta give him cash. אמר רב אסי.
Amar Rav Assi. Okay, now, before we go on. So here, how
do we פוסק, posken, right? Here you go, Michael, Rav Chanan asks
how we פוסק. posken. Before we said it could be if it's
not land, it could be paper clips, and here we're saying land
or cash. Okay, so the רי"ף Rif says it's a מחלוקת, machlokes,
and we פוסק posken like the earlier position. We actually פוסק posken
that it can be paper clips even לכתחילה, lechatchila, even if you're
not doing—if you're not doing land. Okay, but if you look at
תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says the
following. תוספות Tosafot
says ורבינו תם, ve-Rabbeinu Tam, it's like seven lines before the lines
get wide, תוספות רב הונא אמר. Tosafot Rav Huna amar. He says,
and this is important, we—we discussed this issue earlier. רבינו תם אינו
סובר כן. Rabbeinu Tam eino sover kein. He doesn't agree to the
רי"ף Rif that we פוסק לכתחילה posken lechatchila you can give the
guy paper clips by נזיקין. Nezikin. דמפרש שיש ג' דינין בנזיקין. demefaresh
she-yesh gimmel dinin be-Nezikin. There are three categories when it comes—excuse me,
ג' דינין, gimmel dinin, there are three categories when it comes to
paying up debt. בנזיקין, be-Nezikin, if it's damages, או כסף או מיטב.
o kesef o meitav. We פוסק posken like this גמרא: Gemara: either
the best land or cash. And only if you don't have top-quality
land or cash do you give what you have. Okay, but the—but
the first level is top-quality land or cash. ואי לית ליה, ve-ee
leit lei, if you don't have those, then אפילו סובין, afilu subin,
then whatever you've got. ובעל חוב, u-vaal chov,
if you owe money, אי אית ליה זוזי לא מצי לסלקו אלא
בזוזי, ee it lei zuzei lo matzi lesalko ela be-zuzei,
that if you have money, I can't—you the בעל חוב baal chov
can't tell me, 'Take the land.' No, if you've got cash, you've
got to pay me cash. Even מיטב, meitav, you can't have me
take. I gave you cash; you have to give me back cash
if you have cash available. Okay, כדמוכח בהכותב גבי ההוא דאוליף זוזי
בנהרדעי הוה, kademuchach be-HaKotev gabei hahu de-olif zuzei be-Nahardei hava, ואי לית
ליה זוזי, ve-ee leit lei zuzei, לא יאמר לו זיל טרח וזבין
ואייתי זוזי. lo yomar lo zil tarach ve-zavin ve-aiti zuzei.
But if the debtor does not have cash, I can't force him
to sell his property and—and to give me cash; he can just
give me whatever he's got.
כדאמר התם, kadamar hatam, etc., etc. ופועל, u-poel, end of the second
wide line, אי לית ליה לבעל הבית זוזי, ee leit lei le-baal
ha-bayis zuzei, אמר ליה זיל טרח וזבין ואייתי זוזי. amar lei zil
tarach ve-zavin ve-aiti zuzei. Okay, if I
who hired the worker, if I don't have cash, I can't give
the worker anything I've got. I have the responsibility of raising the
cash and paying my workers in cash. Okay, כדמוכח בבית ועלייה דאיכא
למימר ליה טומאה שעשית בשכרך. kademuchach be-Bayis ve-Aliya de-iycha lemeimar lei toma
she-asisa bisecharacha.
Because I can't say to him, I says, 'You know what? You've
been working all day on making shoes. Here, I've got a shoe
factory. I'm a little short on cash. Why not just take home
a hundred pairs of shoes?' Okay, so that would be the הלכה,
halacha, right? Everybody else, if they don't have cash, they can pay
with what they've got. But a worker, you can't pay with what
you've got; a worker you have to pay cash. So it's very
interesting. For נזיקין, Nezikin, top-level land or cash, בדיעבד bedieved whatever you've
got. For בעל חוב, baal chov, cash is the לכתחילה, lechatchila, בדיעבד
bedieved whatever you've got. And for a worker, it absolutely has to
be cash.
Okay, so very interesting to know the different levels of responsibilities in
different types of payment. Back to the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב אסי,
Amar Rav Assi, said Rav Assi, כספים הרי הן
כקרקע. kesafim harei hein ke-karka. Cash, money, is like land. למאי הלכתא?
Lemai hilchata? For what purpose is Rav Assi saying that? אילימא לענין
מיטב, Ilima le-inyan meitav, if it's to tell you מיטב meitav what
we just said
before: either top-level land or cash if you do damages, היינו דרב
הונא. hainu de-Rav Huna. So that's Rav Huna. So just say, you
know, וכן אמר רב אסי. ve-chein amar Rav Assi. Why did you
rephrase it in this funny way? Land is like cash—a cash is
like land. Okay, אלא לשני אחים שחלקו ונטל אחד קרקע ואחד כספים.
ela lishnei achim she-chalku ve-natal echad karka ve-echad kesafim.
So this is going to be similar to some of the issues
we were talking about before. Two brothers divided an estate;
one took the cash and one took the land. ובא בעל חוב
ונטל קרקע. u-va baal chov ve-natal karka. And then a creditor of
their father's comes and took the land because a creditor of the
father didn't have access to the cash; he only had liens on
the land once the person is—the—the borrower is dead or whoever the
מזיק mazik is dead. Okay, he can, he cannot get the cash
or the chattel. He can only get the land. So he went
and he took the land from the son that took the land.
דאזל האי, D'azal hai, the son who took the land goes ושקיל
פלגא בכספים בהדיה. v'shakil palga b'chasafim bahadeih. And he goes to his
other brother and says, give me back half of the, give me
half the cash. Okay? Yes, he took the land, but it was
a land paying up for our father's debt. So I'm entitled to
still half of the remainder of the estate. So give me your
half, give me half of what you took in the cash. Okay?
So הגמרא Ha-Gemara says פשיטא, pshita, obviously that's true. האי ברא והאי
לאו ברא, Hai bra v'hai lav bra, this one is the son
and the other one isn't the son? They're both sons, they're both
entitled to the estate. The land that was seized was seized because
of their father's debt, which means it really came from the estate
in its entirety. So of course they should split what's left. Okay?
So that's interesting. So the גמרא Gemara first says it's פשיטא. pshita.
Then the גמרא Gemara is going to say it's not פשיטא, pshita,
it's actually not true. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, some say אדרבה, adaraba,
להידך גיסא. l'idach gisa. No,
don't say it's פשיטא, pshita, say it's the opposite is true. This
doesn't make sense, you're not entitled to half the cash back. דאמר
ליה, D'amar leih, because the guy who took the cash should say
להכי שקלי כספים, L'hachi shakli k'safim,
that's why I agreed to take the cash. By taking cash I
took a risk and I had a benefit. What was the risk
I took by taking the cash? דאי מגנבי, De-i mignavi, לא משתלמינא
מינך. lo mishtalmina minach.
If cash is more easily stolen than land, so by taking cash
I risked it being stolen. And I implicitly agreed that if something
happened to that money, I would not ask you to reimburse me.
That was the risk I assumed. ולהכי שקלת ארעא, U-l'hachi shaklat ar'a,
by you choosing to take the land you assumed a risk. What
was the risk you assumed? דאי מיטרפא, De-i mitarfa, that if that
land is seized by a debt, לא משתלמינא לך lo mishtalmina lach
מידי מינאי, midi minai, I won't have to pay you anything from
my property. So that's a really good question. What's the הלכה? halacha?
We have two opposite opinions, opinions. We'll get back to it in
a minute. But we still don't know what the הלכה halacha is
about cash as like land. Either it's obvious or it's not true.
Okay. אלא לשני אחים שחלקו, Ela lishnei achim she-chalku,
two brothers divided their estate, and
they both took land. ובא בעל חוב ונטל חלקו של אחד מהן.
U-va ba'al chov u-natal chelko shel echad mehen.
And a creditor came and seized one of the pieces of property.
He could have easily have taken the other one, he just took
one. Okay. והא, V'ha, and that case, so the point, so now
what would that mean that cash is like land? That the guy
whose property wasn't taken has to pay his brother, you know, either
back the land or pay, you know, half of the land that
he took, or give his brother cash for the value of the
land. Because in this case you can't say, these are the risks
I assumed, those are the risks you assumed. We both took land,
so nobody was assuming any special risks. So if any one's lands
are taken, obviously now we're, everybody's entitled to do a redistribution, right?
Because ultimately it was taken on the basis of the debt of
the estate. All right. So the גמרא Gemara says, והא אמר רב
אסי חדא זימנא, V'ha amar Rav Assi chada zimna, Rav Assi already
said this once. דאיתמר, D'itmar, it was taught. האחים שחלקו, Ha-achim she-chalku,
brothers divided all land of the estate. ובא בעל חוב ונטל חלקו
של אחד מהן. U-va ba'al chov u-natal chelko shel echad mehen. And
a creditor came and seized one of the pieces of property. Okay.
רב אמר בטלה מחלוקת. Rav amar batla machloket. Rav says, okay, you
got to do, that came off essentially from the top of the
estate, so now we have to do a whole redistribution of the
property. Again, whether it's technically a redistribution or all the remaining brothers
will chip in and reimburse the guy, but basically it came up
from the top of the estate and everybody's entitled back to having
an equal portion. ושמואל אמר ויתר. U-Shmuel amar vitar. Shmuel says no,
you lost it, you know, this guy lost whatever he, ויתר vitar
literally means like he's מוותר, mevater, he's like, he's, you know, he's
like giving up on his rights. But anyway, he lost out. ורב
אסי אמר נוטל רביע בקרקע ורביע במעות. V'Rav Assi amar notel revia
b'karka u-revia b'maot.
No, actually he has to be reimbursed. So if there's one brother,
but rather than the brother, everybody took a hundred dollar plot of
land, one guy's plot was taken. So the other brother gives him
back fifty dollars, but how does he give him fifty dollars? He
gives him fifty dollars, half of his plot, a quarter, twenty-five dollars
in cash and twenty-five dollars in land. That's very interesting. So let's
see what this is about. ורב אמר בטלה מחלוקת, V'Rav amar batla
machloket, קסבר, kasavar, he is of the opinion, האחים שחלקו כיורשים הוו.
ha-achim she-chalku k'yorshim havu.
Even after they've divided, essentially they still vis-a-vis the land have a
status of heirs. So when property is taken, it's taken like it's
taken from the estate. It's taken like it was taken pre-division. Okay?
They're still fundamentally like heirs vis-a-vis the land and therefore they would
have to redistribute it. Okay? So it's basically מחלוקת רבי יוחנן וריש
לקיש machloket Rabbi Yochanan v'Resh Lakish if האחים שחלקו לקוחות או יורשים.
ha-achim she-chalku likuchot o yorshim. ושמואל אמר ויתר, U-Shmuel amar vitar, קסבר
האחים שחלקו לקוחות. kasavar ha-achim she-chalku likuchot. No,
once you divide the estate, it's basically like I am buying out
your portion in the estate for this and you're buying out my
portion in the estate, you know, for the other thing. So we're
actually, it's not we're still as heirs, we actually have purchased essentially
everybody else's portion from what we have given up in the estate.
And therefore, since it's a purchase What happens? It's a purchase לקוחות
כלוקח שלא באחריות. lakochot kelokeach shelo b'achrayut.
But also, it's a purchase without אחריות, achrayut, without any insurance. So
what happens? The brothers divided it up, okay, and somebody comes, a
בעל חוב ba'al chov comes and takes from Shimon. So here the
question is, we look at Yaakov, Yaakov is the father, we look
at Yaakov's creditor when he's taking from Shimon, not like he's taking
from Yaakov's heir, we look at it like he's taking from Yaakov's
from a purchaser. He took it from somebody who purchased the field.
Okay, so he purchased it. So why does Shimon now have a
right to go to Reuven and have to be reimbursed? Shimon sort
of purchased Reuven's portion by giving up whatever he gave up, but
he did not, there was implicitly no אחריות. achrayut. So whatever Shimon
has to give up, right, he can't go back to, "Oh Reuven,
give me back what I," no, it was essentially sold שלא באחריות.
shelo b'achrayut. And therefore he has no right to get reimbursed from
Reuven. Okay. Now רב אסי Rav Assi אמר, amar, נוטל רביע בקרקע
ורביע
במעות. notel revia b'karka u'revia b'maos. You get, actually Reuven does have
to reimburse, he gives back twenty-five, assuming it goes a hundred dollars,
twenty-five in cash and twenty-five in קרקע. karka. מספקא ליה אי כיורשים
דמו אי כלקוחות דמו. misapka lei i k'yorshim damu i k'lakochot damu.
He doesn't know, are you like a יורש yoresh or like a
לוקח? lokeach? Now Rashi says לוקח lokeach would mean a לוקח באחריות
lokeach b'achrayut as opposed to what Shmuel said, לוקח שלא באחריות. lokeach
shelo b'achrayut. Okay, so he says I know, as opposed to Shmuel,
I know that Reuven has to reimburse Shimon, either from the model
of יורש, yoresh, it was seized from them as heirs and as
the estate, so the estate has to get redistributed, or even if
the model is that they purchased from one another, implicitly it was
a purchase with אחריות. achrayut. So either way Reuven has to make
good for Shimon. Okay, but here's the difference. If it was because
of יורש, yoresh, then you would redistribute the קרקע. karka. If it
was because of אחריות, achrayut, right? If I sell you land and
it's seized from you and you come to me, I pay you
not with קרקע karka but with cash. You get it? So clearly
I gotta reimburse Shimon, I just don't know if I reimburse Shimon
with קרקע karka because of יורש yoresh or with cash because of
לוקח באחריות. lokeach b'achrayut. So therefore I do it half and half.
Okay. הלכך נוטל רביע בקרקע ורביע במעות. hilkach notel revia b'karka u'revia
b'maos. Alright, so anyway to the degree that we said כספים הרי
הן כקרקע, kesafim harei hen k'karka, if it meant anything like these
issues of brothers that divide, so either it's obvious or it's not
true, or in this case it was already somewhat said that I
have to reimburse my brother with both cash and land, and the
cash serves somewhat like the land. אלא מאי הרי הן כקרקע? ela
mai harei hen k'karka? Fine. So go back to what we said
before. What does it mean cash is like land? לעניין מיטב, l'inyan
meitav, like we said before, like like who had said, like Rav
Huna said, that when you pay for נזק, nezek, you either pay
with cash or you pay with top-level land or with cash, not
with paperclips. אי הכי היינו דרב הונא. iy hachi hainu d'Rav Huna.
So then just say, so that's Rav Huna, why did you say
it in this funny way, cash is like land? אימא רב הונא
וכן רב אסי. eima Rav Huna v'chen Rav Assi. Don't say it
in a fancy new way. Rav Huna says cash or land and
Rav Assi says the same thing. He's not saying anything different. But
in the interim we had this fascinating discussion of when brothers divide
an estate how much they are, you know, equally responsible for debts
of the father that will be seized. Okay. Now, before we end
this whole very fascinating discussion about מיטב meitav and grades of land
and all that thing, and I think particularly this question here at
the end about whether you have to pay back debts in cash
or in other types of things, we get to another issue that
has to do with money, but other than the fact that it
has to do with sort of money I'm not exactly sure what
it's doing in this גמרא. Gemara. But it's a very important issue
להלכה. l'halacha. So let's take a look. אמר רבי זירא אמר רב
הונא, amar Rabbi Zeira amar Rav Huna, במצוה עד שליש. b'mitzvah ad
shalish.
When it comes to doing מצוות, mitzvot, it should be up to
a third of your net worth. What a third? So מאי שליש?
mai shalish? What does that mean? אילימא שליש ביתו, eileima shalish beito,
that you have to pay a third of your net worth in
order to do a מצוה. mitzvah. So Rashi says let's say look
at Rashi. שליש ביתו, shalish beito, top of דף יב עמוד ב,
daf yud bet amud bet, שחייב אדם לבזבז במצוה לולב וציצית וספר
תורה שליש מה שיש לו. shechayav adam l'vazbez b'mitzvah lulav v'tzitzit v'sefer
torah shalish mah sheyesh lo. If I have a מצוה, mitzvah,
I have to spend up to a third of my property. Here's
a very important halachic question.
In order to not do a negative command, a לא תעשה, lo
ta'aseh, right? You have to be willing, if somebody says I'm going
to burn down your house unless you eat this piece of חזיר,
chazir, okay?
Unless
you say לשון הרע, lashon hara, okay, unless you shave off your
פאות, peyos, you would have to let them burn down your house.
You'd have to give up all of your wealth before being עובר
over on a לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh. How much though to passively
not do a מצות עשה? mitzvot aseh? How much money do I
have to spend to do a, to do a מצות עשה? mitzvot
aseh? Oh, that costs too much, I'm just not going to take
לולב ואתרוג lulav v'etrog this year.
Oh, not perform a מצוה?
mitzvah? No, no, okay, well that's going to be the resolution, but
that's not what we're saying right now. Okay. I'm a עני, ani,
I have very little money, to buy a לולב lulav would be
basically I'd have to borrow money to buy a לולב, lulav, I'd
have to use all of my... all of my income, all of
my money to buy a לולב. lulav. How much? To say up
more than a third you don't have to do, right? Which is
interesting, right? In one way, you could say it's maybe it's very
מחמיר. machmir. You have to spend a third of your income, but
also it's your income
or your— oh, I'm sorry, net worth.
מר Mar says 'ביתא', beisa, right now we're saying net worth. Okay.
So it's it's more מיקל meikel than a לא תעשה lo sa'asei
where you had to be where even if you were to lose
all your money you shouldn't transgress, but still a lot to spend
for a מצוה, mitzvah, right? A third of your net worth. By
the way, that's the חידוש chiddush by the משנה mishna in ערבי
פסחים Arvei Psachim of אפילו אפילו עני בישראל, afilu afilu ani b'Yisrael,
right, you know, what is it?
you know, what's the how does what's the משנה mishna say?
Yeah, so he has to do ארבע כוסות, arba kosos, I'm just
trying to think of the לשון. lashon. Anyway,
לא יסב— lo yeisheiv no, לא
יפחתו
לו,
lo yifchesu
lo,
thank you, לא יפחתו לו מארבע כוסות. lo yifchesu lo mei'arba kosos.
They shouldn't give him less than ארבע כוסות. arba kosos. So who
is that referring to? So the רשב"ם Rashbam says that's actually referring
to the גבאי צדקה gabai tzedaka that you shouldn't say like, hey,
this is communal צדקה tzedaka fund, we'll pay for your meal, we're
not going to pay for you to have four glasses of wine.
No, no, no, we have to use צדקה tzedaka funds to give
him four glasses of wine. But others say the חידוש chiddush is
on the עני ani that even though normally for מצוות mitzvos you're
not you don't have to spend more than a certain amount of
money to do מצוות, mitzvos, on ליל סדר Leil Seder to show
how wealthy and free you are, you have to spend all your
money to do these four cups of wine. But anyway, but that's
the question: how much do you have to spend? So אימא שליש
ביתו, eima shelish beiso, if it means a third of your house,
meaning a third of your net worth, אלא מעתה איסתמי ותלתא מצוותא,
ela mei'ata isrami v'tlasa mitzvasa, if you had three מצוות mitzvos there
to do, ליתיב לכולי ביתיה? leiseiv l'kulei beisei? You have to give
up your whole house? אלא אמר רב זירא, ela amar Rav Zeira,
yes,
which isn't technically true because you'd take a third of the rest.
Right, you could always do a third of the next. But that's
why I think it says if they were all three at the
same time, you don't get to say a third of the next.
Okay. אלא אמר זירא בהידור מצוה עד שליש במצוה, ela amar Zeira
b'hiddur mitzvah ad shelish b'mitzvah, עד שליש במצוה. ad shelish b'mitzvah. When
it comes to a הידור מצוה, hiddur mitzvah, you have to be
prepared to spend a third more than you would have spent just
to do the מצוה mitzvah itself. So the way רש"י Rashi says
it is, let's say I see this nice כשר kosher אתרוג esrog
for sixty dollars, okay? How much more should I spend to get
not just a כשר kosher אתרוג, esrog, but a מהודר mehudar אתרוג?
esrog? You should spend a third more. Okay, now the question is:
how do you determine your baseline? Meaning רש"י Rashi says you have
one אתרוג esrog in front of you, how much more should I
spend and shop around for a nicer one? But let's say I
go into the market and I know I can get barely כשר
kosher for ten dollars. They say חינוך chinuch set. It's כשר, kosher,
but it's a חינוך chinuch set, okay, for ten dollars. Or I
could get nice but not מהודר mehudar for fifty dollars, and I
get מהודר mehudar for two hundred dollars. Do I start at the
ten dollar watermark or do I start at the fifty dollar mark?
Not clear. Anyway, yes, John?
I actually asked this question Rabbi once about the movie אושפיזין Ushpizin
where the guy spends a thousand shekel on an אתרוג, esrog, which
is way more.
Right, right, right. Not exactly כדין והלכה. kedin v'halacha. Anyway, okay, בהידור
מצוה עד שליש במצוה. b'hiddur mitzvah ad shelish b'mitzvah. בעי רב אשי:
ba'ei Rav Ashi: שליש מלגאו או שליש מלבר? shelish miligav o shelish
milibar? Always the גמרא's Gemara math question: do you determine the third
from the inside or the outside? Meaning if it starts at sixty
dollars,
a third of what the current price is, so which is twenty
dollars, add twenty. Or do I say the amount I spend at
the end should have been a third of the total? I should
spend thirty dollars more, so then ninety would be the total in
the
end and the thirty dollars I added would be a third of
ninety. Do you understand? Right, if I have my base, if X
is my base, is it thirty-three percent of X or is it—
what would be the other one? Fifty percent of X. Right. Okay,
that's the question. Okay, so תיקו. teiku. So we don't know. גמרא
אמרי משמיה משמיה דרבי זירא: Gemara amri mishmei mishmei d'Rabbi Zeira: עד
שליש משלו. ad shelish mishalo. The first third you spend for הידור
מצוה hiddur mitzvah is coming out of your pocket. מכאן ואילך משל
הקדוש ברוך הוא. mi'kan v'eilach mishel Hakadosh Baruch Hu. After that, it's
coming out of God's pocket. It doesn't mean you can tell the
guy you bought it from, get it from God. It means God
is promising to pay you back for that.
Meaning you should spend more anyway.
Right, right, it's sort of like by שבת, Shabbos, you know, לוו
עלי ואני פורע. luvu alai v'ani poreia. Spend the money, I'll pay
you back for it. Anyway, what we're left with is an interesting
question, which is: how much do I have to spend, not just
for הידור מצוה, hiddur mitzvah, but to do a מצוה? mitzvah? Right?
What is the limit of doing a מצוה? mitzvah? So in terms
of מצות עשה. mitzvas asei. So if you look at תוספות: Tosafos:
אימא שליש ביתו, eima shelish beiso, תוספות Tosafos says משמע דאין צריך
לבזבז כל ממונו לקנות אתרוג אפילו לא ימצא בפחות mashma d'ein tzarich
levazveiz kol mamono liknos esrog afilu lo yimtza b'pachos והוי מצות עשה,
v'havi mitzvas asei, even if you'll totally lose doing the מצוה. mitzvah.
אפילו שליש ביתו משמע דלא מחייב afilu shelish beiso mashma d'lo mechayeiv
in the conclusion of the גמרא. Gemara. ואמרינן נמי המבזבז, v'amrinan nami
hamivazveiz, if you want to squander your money, meaning give away your
money for צדקה, tzedaka, אל יבזבז יותר מחומש. al yivazveiz yoseir michomesh.
You shouldn't give away more than twenty percent of your money for
צדקה. tzedaka. ובסוכה חשיב ליה רבותא דרבן גמליאל שקנה אתרוג באלף זוז.
ub'Sukkah chashiv lei rivusa d'Rabban Gamliel shekana esrog b'elef zuz. There you
go, the אושפיזין ushpizin movie. Oh, רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, look how
much money he spent! So clearly there's a limit to how much
you have to spend, but תוספות Tosafot doesn't tell you what the
limit is. Okay, now a lot of פוסקים poskim gravitate to the
אל יבזבז יותר מחומש. al y'vazbez yoter me'chomesh. But that's still different.
There, I'm anyway being, I mean you could say it both ways.
Number way is I'm anyway being מקיים m'kayem the מצוה mitzvah of
צדקה tzedakah by my first dollar. So maybe it's different if I
wouldn't be מקיים m'kayem the מצוה mitzvah at all. Maybe I'd have
to spend more than a חומש. chomesh. On the other hand, you
could say that's not telling me I have to spend a חומש.
chomesh. That's actually setting a limit. Don't overspend. Like, you know, the
whole Christian idea was, you know, give away all your money to
the poor and devote yourself to God. Of course, the poor don't
do so well in that situation. I mean, you know, it's better
you should continue to earn money and not make yourself poor and
keep on giving. Okay, so that's telling me I'm not allowed to
give more than a חומש. chomesh. That's not telling me how much
I'm obligated to give to avoid doing a מצוה. mitzvah. And the
other question has to do with again, are we talking about your
net worth? Are we talking about your income? So this issue really,
often פוסקים poskim quote the idea of a fifth, but it's not
really fully... the רמ"א Rama I believe פוסק paskens in הלכות לולב,
Hilchos Lulav, I think he פוסק, paskens, let me see if I
can quickly pick it up. I think he
פוסק paskens a fifth, but... yeah, Charlie, yes your
question?
Yeah, so in the Middle Ages in Europe,
the huge number of people who were abandoning all their property allegedly
for the poor caused huge social problems. Right, because there are all
these poor people, voluntarily poor people running around.
Right, and nobody's earning the money.
Right. So I think the רמ"א Rama פוסק paskens here...
one minute.
ומי שאין לו אתרוג, U'mi she'ein lo etrog, this is in תרנ"ו
Taf Reish Nun Vav in הלכות... Hilchos... first the שולחן ערוך Shulchan
Aruch פוסק paskens הידור מצוה עד שליש. hiddur mitzvah ad shelish. The
רמ"א Rama says on there תרנ"ו Taf Reish Nun Vav in אורח
חיים: Orach Chaim: ומי שאין לו אתרוג או שאר מצוה עוברת אין
צריך לבזבז עליהן הון רב, u'mi she'ein lo etrog o she'ar mitzvah
overet ein tzarich levazbez aleihen hon rav, you don't have to spend
an enormous amount of money, וכמו שאמרנו המבזבז אל יבזבז יותר מחומש
אפילו מצוה עוברת, u'k'mo she'amarnu ham'vazbez al y'vazbez yoter me'chomesh afilu mitzvah
overet, ודוקא מצות עשה אבל לא תעשה יתן כל ממונו. ve'davka mitzvat
aseh aval lo ta'aseh yitein kol mamono. So he says like תוספות.
Tosafot. You don't have to spend an enormous amount of money. Like
we say by צדקה, tzedakah, you don't give more than a fifth.
Okay, but how much
do I have to spend? Do I have to spend a fifth?
Again, by צדקה tzedakah it's an upper limit, it's not a minimum.
What?
And is that income or wealth?
Is it income? Right. Is it income or net worth? What?
A fifth can be enormous. It could...
well, that's also true. Right. But right. Meaning, let's say you're a
billionaire. Do I have to spend a fifth? Right. So anyway, so
that's where the רמ"א Rama quotes it, but it's never really articulated
what that minimum is and right, the difference between income and wealth
is a big issue, but often you hear the number of a
fifth thrown around. Okay, let's start the next
משנה. Mishnah. כל שחבתי בשמירתו הכשרתי את נזקו. Kol she'chavti b'shmirato hichsharti
et nizko. Now this משנה Mishnah is sort of like a riddle.
Okay? I mean, this obviously seems to reflect a very early משנה
Mishnah because it's written in this more archaic language. You might remember
that the previous משנה Mishnah ended that the basic obligation is that
ממונך ושמירתן עליך וכשהזיק חב המזיק לשלם בתשלומי הארץ. mamonecha u'shmiratan alecha
u'ksh'hizik chav hamazik l'shalem b'tashlumei ha'aretz. So the phrase was חב, chav,
as opposed to חייב, chayav, right, חב המזיק לשלם. chav hamazik l'shalem.
And this is going to be חב המזיק לשלם. chav hamazik l'shalem.
Now what's interesting about that, in addition to the word חב chav
which is חייב chayav or whatever, is it's calling me the מזיק.
mazik. Even though I didn't do any damage, my animals did the
damage. So let's see what this משנה Mishnah says. This משנה Mishnah
seems to be a clarification of that.
כל שחבתי בשמירתו, Kol she'chavti b'shmirato, anything I'm obligated to watch, okay,
so there's that word חב chav again,
הכשרתי את נזקו. hichsharti et nizko. It is like I have prepared
the damage. If I am... it seems to be what it's saying,
רש"י Rashi has two explanations, but seems to be what it's saying
is if I have an obligation to watch and I'm negligent, then
it's like I made the damage happen. And that seems to phrase...
remember the question we asked on day one: why am I obligated
when my property does damage or my animals do damage? Is it
because it's like I did the damage and it's just sort of
strict liability, they did it, I pay for it? Or is it
because my negligence means that I'm to blame and therefore it's like
I... and therefore it's because of my negligence that I'm paying? And
this משנה Mishnah seems to say B. If I was obligated to
watch it, it's like I have made the damage happen. It's like
I've prepared the damage.
הכשרתי במקצת נזקו חבתי בתשלומי נזקו כהכשר כל נזקו. Hichsharti b'miktzat nizko
chavti b'tashlumei nizko k'hechsher kol nizko. Even if I only
sort
of prepared some of the damage, maybe only a partial negligence, I
will have to pay for all the damage that occurs. We'll see
what that means in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. נכסים
שאין בהן מעילה. Nechasim she'ein bahen me'ilah. Now what do I have
to pay for? Only the damages property that there is no מעילה
me'ilah for, no misuse of הקדש, hekdesh, meaning it's חולין. chullin. All
of these phrases are very... are archaic sort of phrases, okay, so
it's a way of saying like חולין chullin or not הקדש. hekdesh.
It doesn't have מעילה. me'ilah. נכסים שהם Nechasim she'hem נכסים שהן של
בני ברית *nechasim she-hen shel bnei brit*, they are owned by members,
by members of the tribe, okay? That's what I have to pay
for. And נכסים המיוחדים *nechasim ha-miyuchadim*, spec-
singled or distinguished or whatever which basically the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
going to say means owned property as opposed to ownerless property, which
should be pretty obvious, who am I going to pay ownerless property
to? ובכל מקום *U-ve-chol makom*, and I have to pay for it
wherever the damage occurs, חוץ *chutz*, one place I am free from
liability is רשות המיוחדת למזיק *reshut ha-miyuchadet la-mazik*. If it's my property,
you bring your thing into my property and it gets damaged, as
I said, like, you know, what are you doing in my property
without permission? Now the point being without permission, right? Because normally if
I let you into my property with permission, at least in contemporary
law, that's when I have the greatest responsibility, right? That's why you
buy homeowners insurance, right? But if you come into my property without
permission, I can say, hey buddy, you know, I am not responsible
if you're on my property. רשות הניזק והמזיק *Reshut ha-nizak ve-ha-mazik*, or
if it is a jointly owned property, which is interesting. Why should
I be exempt on a jointly owned property? You had a right
to be there. We'll see in the גמרא *Gemara*. In all those
cases, back to the language from the משנה Mishnah *Mishna*, from the
first משנה Mishnah *Mishna*, כשהזיק חב המזיק לשלם תשלומי נזק במיטב הארץ
*keshe-hizik chav ha-mazik leshalem tashlumei nezek be-meitav ha-aretz*. That's the last line
of the first משנה *Mishna*. Okay, but you see that this is
a very like, you know, cryptic, you know, language. It's almost like
a riddle. Let's take a look at the גמרא *Gemara*. תנו רבנן
*Tanu rabanan*: כל שחבתי בשמירתו הכשרתי את נזקו כיצד *kol she-chavti bi-shmirato
hichsharti et nizko keitzad*? What does it mean that if I sort
of like, you know, was obligated, then I'm to blame? Okay, so
שור shor ובור שמסר לחרש שוטה וקטן והזיקו חייב *shor u-vor she-masar
le-cheresh shote ve-katan ve-hiziku chayav*. I gave an ox or a pit
to a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh ve'katan *cheresh shote ve-katan* to
watch and then damage occurred. Surprise, surprise. I'm חייב לשלם *chayav leshalem*
because I was to blame. I was obligated to watch it. I
wasn't responsible in the watching, I gave it to a חרש שוטה
וקטן cheresh shoteh ve'katan *cheresh shote ve-katan*. Anything that happens is my
fault. Okay, so מה שאין כן באש *ma she-ein ken be-eish*. Now
we throw in something that's not in the משנה *Mishna* at all,
and we just make a point that, oh by the way, if
you gave a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh ve'katan. *cheresh shote ve-katan*
a fire to watch, you're not so responsible, which is like, what?
So let's take a look. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, במה עסקינן
*be-mai askinan*? What's the case? אילימא בשור קשור ובור מכוסה *Ilima be-shor
kashur u-vor mechuseh*, the ox was tied down and the pit was
covered, so the thing in its current state was protected. And that's
why I am, you know, so then, so first of all why
am I חייב *chayav* by the חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh ve'katan
*cheresh shote ve-katan*, right? Presumably because they might actually, well we'll see,
they might ruin what's been done to protect it or whatever. בדכוותיה
גבי אש esh *Bid-chavateih gabei eish*, also why is it given in
fire? What would be the parallel by fire? Something that's a protected
fire? גחלת gachelet, *Gachelet*. It's like a coal, it's not like a
live flame. מאי שנא הכא ומאי שנא הכא *Mai shna hacha u-mai
shna hacha*? Why in one case am I חייב *chayav* and in
one case I'm פטור *patur*, right? If they're both basically protected, either
be פטור *patur* in both or חייב *chayav* in both. אלא בשור
מותר ובור מגולה *Ela be-shor mutar u-vor meguleh*, it must be that
the ox is unbound and the pit is exposed, and that's why
I'm חייב *chayav* by the חרש שוטה וקטן *cheresh shote ve-katan*. So
if that's the case, what's the parallel? דכוותיה גבי אש *Bid-chavateih gabei
eish*, the parallel by the fire is שלהבת *shalevet*, a flame. מה
שאין כן באש דפטור *Ma she-ein ken be-eish de-patur*. Why am I
exempt by a flame? It's an exposed hazard. Why does giving it
to a חרש שוטה וקטן *cheresh shote ve-katan*...
I gave him a torch? Or he's burning in a field?
One of the other. Okay, we'll see, I mean, whatever, you obviously
might be a big difference. והא אמר ריש לקיש משמיה דחזקיה *Ve-ha
amar Reish Lakish mi-shmei de-Chizkiyah*, ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* says in the
name of חזקיה *Chizkiyah*, לא שנו *lo shanu*, when is it when
you give something to a חרש שוטה וקטן *cheresh shote ve-katan* a
fire you're פטור *patur*? אלא שמסר לו גחלת וליבה *Ela she-masar lo
gachelet ve-libah*. You gave him an ember and the חרש שוטה וקטן
*cheresh shote ve-katan* blew it into a flame. In that case, I'm
exempt because obviously it was the חרש *cheresh* who decided to make
it into a flame, that wasn't the way I gave it to
him. Okay, אבל בשלהבת חייב *aval be-shalevet chayav*. But if you gave
him a flame, a live flame, I'm חייב *chayav*. מאי טעמא דברי
היזיקא *Mai ta'ama de-vari heizeika*? Because the damage is likely. Okay, so
basically there's two ways you could frame the question. At what stage
am I פטור *patur* when I give something to a חרש שוטה
וקטן *cheresh shote ve-katan*? What's the likelihood that they'll help or not
help or what's the likelihood that they'll make it worse? Okay, but
the other question is, why should a fire be different from a
שור shor *shor* and a בור bor *vor*? Okay, so let's see
what the גמרא *Gemara*'s answer is. The גמרא *Gemara* says, לעולם בשור
קשור ובור מכוסה *Le-olam be-shor kashur u-vor mechuseh*, the ox is bound
and the well is sealed, ודכוותיה גבי אש גחלת *ve-did-chavateih gabei eish
gachelet*, and by the אש *eish* it would be an ember. ודקאמרת
מאי שנא הכא ומאי שנא הכא *Ve-dik'amart mai shna hacha u-mai shna
hacha*? Why are you חייב *chayav* in the first case and exempt
in the second? שור דרכיה לנתוקי *Shor darcheih lenatukei*, בור bor, דרכיה
לנתורי *vor darcheih lenaturei*, because an ox will naturally, it will
work itself free from its bounds, and a well, you know, the
cover sometimes will get uncovered, people will step on it or whatever,
and therefore, even though it's protected, you need somebody responsible to be
watching it and to make sure. sure that it retains its current
state. The current state is not stable. No, but an ember, it's
like an ember. Okay, embers die out under natural circumstances. גחלת כמה
דשבית לה, if you just leave it alone, מאמיא מאמיא ואזל, ma'amya
ma'amya ve'azel, it'll just burn itself out. So one case, if you
leave it... one case you could have left unattended, the other case
needed to be attended. And if it needed to be attended, having
a חרש שוטה וקטן doing it is not doing your responsibility. But
by a גחלת, it doesn't really need to be attended, so you're
exempt. By the way, I explained it the way רשי Rashi did,
תוספות Tosafot says that the שור and the בור are only going
to get undone means that the חרש שוטה וקטן are going to
fool around and they're going to make it undone. They're going to
leave alone an ember, you know, you don't play with fire. But
an ox, oh look, let's just... you like playing with oxen, I
guess, or whatever. Anyway, תוספות Tosafot says they make it worse. Okay,
רשי Rashi says they just don't make it better, they just don't
do the necessary sort of observing which is needed, but the ember
doesn't really need to be observed. That's one way. And we'll just
read the last way here, רבי יוחנן דאמר, Rabbi Yochanan de'amar, רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says, אפילו מסר לו שלהבת נמי פטור, afilu masar
lo shalhevet nami patur,
even a flame you're exempt by a חרש שוטה וקטן. Presumably he
feels that they can be doing a reasonable job of protecting it.
So if that's true, דכוותה הכא בשור מותר בור מגולה, dechvata hacha
beshor mutar bor meguleh, it's an undone ox and an exposed well.
מאי שנא הכא מאי שנא התם? mai shena hacha mai shena hatam?
Why by the flame are you exempt and why are you liable
by the ox, right? So it says, no, התם צבתא דחרש קא
גרים הכא לאו צבתא דחרש קא גרים. hatam tzavta decheresh ka garim
hacha lav tzavta decheresh ka garim. In the case by the flame,
the reason you're exempt, now this is a very strange idea and
you know, the reason you're exempt by the flame is because in
the end if the guy if the חרש שוטה וקטן takes the
torch and they light something with it, so it's true like you
were negligent that you gave them the torch, but at the end
of the day they also they did something. They actually put the
torch against something. So it's funny, you would think that only the
act of a בן דעת ben da'at would take it away from
my act. But it's sort of my negligence but another human being's
act. And that sort of gets you off the hook by the...
that's a really big חידוש. chiddush. But by the שור and the
בור, they don't go ahead and gore the other person, they don't
go ahead and push the other person in the well. So they
might be negligent but I... but it's all about negligence then and
I am the primary negligent party. Okay? So in all cases I'm
negligent, but in the case by the fire they're the ones who
did
it.
Wait, if צבתא דחרש, tzavta decheresh, then what are what are they
supposed to do then?
They have something that matters. Either they're not negligent at all, or
they're negligent but it doesn't matter because I was negligent by giving
it to them. So in all cases I have negligence, but the
big חידוש chiddush is when they act when they as a conscious
human being lit, you know, did something, even if they're not liable,
somehow that gets me off the hook. It's a big חידוש. chiddush.
We're going to have later we will later see the סוגיא sugya
of רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש Rabbi Yochanan veReish Lakish directly. Here we're
just referring to it and then we'll be more able to explore
רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. But רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is a big
חידוש. chiddush. But for us the point to take away is, it's
the גמרא chose to bring in the issue that אש is an
exception, but the real point of the משנה is to focus on
my negligence and that that's really important in framing why are you
obligated when your animals do damage, and this משנה says because it's
like you did it because you were negligent. And it emphasizes your
negligence as like you were bringing about the damage that was going
to occur, yeah.